A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs, Series Q FA326
Rockefeller Archive Center
- National Defense
  - National Defense - Air Youth of America, 1941-1948 (Box 18, Folder 147)
    Financial analysis of organization during 1941, dependence on family contributions. Decision to liquidate by merging with National Aeronautical Association and Boy Scouts. Family contributions $53, 663 (1938-1942). Final report to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include R. B. Marston, Arthur W. Packard.
    173.12
  - National Defense - Air Youth of America - Address by Laurance S. Rockefeller - April 24, 1941 and March 20, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 148)
    Endorsement of Air Youth of America's work.
  - National Defense - Air Youth of America - By-laws, 1940 (Box 18, Folder 149)
    Constitution and by-laws of Air Youth of America (AYA).
  - National Defense - Air Youth of America - Contributions and Loans, 1938-1942 (Box 18, Folder 150)
    Contributions made by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Winthrop Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller. Acknowledged contributions made by others. Family aided Winthrop Rockefeller in paying off back loan he guaranteed when Air Youth was liquidated. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Winthrop Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller.
  - National Defense - Air Youth of America - Contributions and Loans, 1938-1942 (Box 18, Folder 0150A)
  - National Defense - Air Youth of America - Scrapbook, 1940-1941 (Box 18, Folder 151)
  - National Defense - Civil Defense, 1941-1949 (Box 18, Folder 152)
    Small family contributions to local civil defense organizations. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller.
    173.13
  - National Defense - Civil Defense, 1941-1949 (Box 18, Folder 0152A)
  - National Defense - Civil Defense - New York City Council of Defense, 1941-1943 (Box 18, Folder 153)
    Nelson A. Rockefeller served on Council, B. P. Turnbull represented him during absence in Washington. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, B. P. Turnbull, F. H. LaGuardia.
  - National Defense - Civil Defense - Civilian Defense Volunteer Office, Greater New York, 1942-1943 (Box 18, Folder 154)
    Information on work of office. Contribution of $2,500 by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - National Defense - Civil Defense - Westchester County Civil Defense, 1951 (Box 18, Folder 155)
    County defense preparation. Clippings only.
  - National Defense - Civil Defense - New York Office of Civil Defense, 1950-1952 (Box 18, Folder 156)
    Information regarding defense plans during Korean conflict. No Rockefeller action. Correspondents include David Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - National Defense - Civil Defense - New York Office of Civil Defense, 1950-1952 (Box 18, Folder 0156A)
  - National Defense - United Defense Fund, 1951-1953 (Box 18, Folder 157)
    Agency to raise funds for civilian war-related services and armed forces services. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel.
    173.31
  - National Defense - United Defense Fund - Westchester County Committee for the United Defense Fund, Inc., 1951-1953 (Box 18, Folder 158)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gift of $1,000 in 1951, 1953, 1952.
  - National Defense - National Aeronautic Association, March 1940-September 1942 (Box 19, Folder 159)
    Absorbed Air Youth of America in 1942. Worked to promote interest of youth in aviation. Packard had a direct control over management of Youth program by his criticism of program and because of Laurance S. Rockefeller's contributions to work. Developing program of cooperation with Girl Scouts and Boy Scouts. Laurance S. Rockefeller resigned from Board in 1944. Contributions by Winthrop cut off in 1945. Laurance S. Rockefeller made several special small contributions 1950-1956. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, Winthrop Rockefeller.
    173.14
  - National Defense - National Aeronautic Association, October 1942-February 1958 (Box 19, Folder 160)
  - National Defense - National Aeronautic Association - Contributions, 1941-1956 (Box 19, Folder 161)
    Exhaustive report on family participation. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Winthrop Rockefeller.
  - National Defense - Air Training Organizations, 1941-1959 (Box 19, Folder 162)
    Requests for aid to various civilian training organizations. All declined. Air Training Corporation of America, Civil Air Patrol, etc. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    173.15
  - National Defense - Airport Authority Bill, January 1946-September 1946 (Box 19, Folder 163)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller, J. H. Doolittle and H. F. Guggenheim appointed commissioners of New York Airport Authority in 1946. Authority tried to plan a program for New York airports, build a staff. R. Moses interfered. Doolittle and Guggenheim resigned. Laurance S. Rockefeller carried on alone. Airport jurisdiction transferred in 1947 to Port of New York Authority by state legislature after long battle. Authority folds Aairport. Staff and programs plans attempted for New York airports here. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, R. Moses, C. W. Newhall (represented Laurance S. Rockefeller on details).
    173.16
  - National Defense - Airport Authority Bill, October 1946-January 1950 (Box 19, Folder 164)
  - National Defense - Airport Authority - New York City - Printed Material, 1946-1947 (Box 19, Folder 165)
    Copies of reports to Mayor by Airport Authority and Port of New York Authority. Also, construction brochures for airport hangers and a report by the Regional Plan Association.
  - National Defense - Airport Authority - New York City - Radar Installation, 1946-1947 (Box 19, Folder 166)
    Under guidance of Newhall of Rockefellers' office. New York City and airlines install experimental radar set at LaGuardia for bad weather flying. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, C. Newhall.
  - National Defense - Airport Authority - New York City - Laurance Rockefeller's Appointment, 1946-1947 (Box 19, Folder 167)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller accepts appointment to commission. Resigns in 1947 when Port Authority takes over airports. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - National Defense - New York City Airport Authority Bill - Report to Mayor, November 1946-January 1947 (Box 20, Folder 168)
    Airport Authority and Port Authority submitted separate reports on New York airports to Mayor in January 1947. Each authority criticized the other's statements. Laurance S. Rockefeller spoke in favor of Airport Authority's plan. Mayor O'Dwyer favored Airport plan. But New York legislature finally decided in favor of New York Port Authority. Also, Port Authority report to Mayor, December 18, 1946. Correspondents include C. W. Newhall, Robert Moses, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - National Defense - New York City Airport Authority Bill - Report to Mayor, January 1947 (Box 20, Folder 169)
  - National Defense - New York City Airport Authority Bill - Report to Mayor, January 1947-March 1947 (Box 20, Folder 170)
  - National Defense - New York City Airport Authority - Floyd Bennett Field, 1946-1947 (Box 20, Folder 171)
    To relieve congestion at LaGuardia while Idlewild was being built city leased part of Floyd Bennett Field from Navy for commercial airline traffic. Correspondents include Robert Moses, C. W> Newhall, Naval personnel.
    173.16F
  - National Defense - New York City Airport Authority - Idlewild Airport, April 1945-November 1946 (Box 20, Folder 172)
    Discussions of construction and planning of Idlewild. Correspondents include Robert Moses, Laurance S. Rockefeller, C. W. Newhall.
    173.16I
  - National Defense - New York City Airport Authority - Idlewild Airport, December 1946-April 1949 (Box 20, Folder 173)
  - National Defense - New York City Airport Authority - LaGuardia Field, 1946-1947 (Box 20, Folder 174)
    Report to Laurance S. Rockefeller on reconstruction program at LaGuardia. Correspondents include Robert Moses.
    173.16L
  - National Defense - Aircraft Industries Association of America, Inc., 1946-1956 (Box 20, Folder 175)
    Information on organization. No Rockefeller participation. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller.
    173.17
  - National Defense - Civil Aeronautics Authority (or Board), 1940-1947 (Box 20, Folder 176)
    Reports on activities, no active Rockefeller participation. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    173.19
  - National Defense - Civil Defense Research Associates, 1954 (Box 20, Folder 177)
    Printed material on industrial security. Correspondents include Yorke Allen.
    173C
  - National Defense - National Defense Letters of Recommendation, 1941-1944 (Box 21, Folder 178)
    Letters by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laurance S. Rockefeller, and Nelson A. Rockefeller recommending men they personally knew for positions as officers in the armed services. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laurance S. Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller.
    173L
  - National Defense - Air Youth of America - Organization, 1941 (Box 47, Folder 415)
    Detailed outline and planning of many aspects of the organization and administration of the Air Youth of America (AYA). Includes sample form appeals signed by Laurance S. Rockefeller. Winthrop Rockefeller served as chairman.
  - National Defense - Air Youth of America - Contribution Prospects
    - 1940 (Box 47, Folder 416)
      Lists of prospective contributors and copies of correspondence with them. Prospects pursued by Winthrop Rockefeller and Thomas Beck. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Winthrop Rockefeller, Thomas Beck.
    - Winthrop Rockefeller - "Preferred" Prospects, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 417)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller - Additional Prospects, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 418)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller - Council Member Letters, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 419)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller - Special Letters, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 420)
    - Beck - "Preferred" Prospects, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 421)
    - Beck - Additional Prospects - Special Letters, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 422)
    - Beck - Prospects Who Have Already Contributed (Before Campaign), 1940 (Box 47, Folder 423)
    - Beck - "Preferred" and "Special" Prospects, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 424)
    - Beck - National Sponsors, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 425)
    - Beck - Unassigned Prospects, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 426)
    - Beck - National Council Members, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 427)
    - Proof - Preliminary Statement of National Sponsors, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 428)
    - Sponsors - Acceptance and Refusal Letters, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 429)
    - Abbreviated Winthrop Rockefeller Sponsor Letter, February 26, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 430)
    - Full Winthrop Rockefeller Sponsor Letter, February 23, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 431)
  - National Defense - Air Youth of America - Minutes and By-Laws, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 432)
    The minutes and bylaws of the Air Youth of America (AYA) from January 1940 to January 1942.
  - National Defense - Air Youth of America - Minutes and By-Laws, 1941-1942 (Box 47, Folder 433)
- Post War Reconstruction
  - Post War Reconstruction, 1943-1944 (Box 21, Folder 179)
    Various plans sent to John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    197
  - Post War Reconstruction - Committee for Economic Development, 1942-1949 (Box 21, Folder 180)
    Invitations to dinner, to become trustee. Nelson A. Rockefeller contribution. Activities, reports. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Paul G. Hoffman.
    197.1
  - Post War Reconstruction - Committee for Economic Development, 1950 (Box 21, Folder 181)
  - Post War Reconstruction - Committee for Economic Development, 1951 (Box 21, Folder 182)
- Peace Plans
  - Peace Plans - World Conditions - National Policy, 1940-1945 (Box 22, Folder 183)
    Plans for peace, studies of causes of the war, defense of America. John F. Dulles' views on war and peace, discussed by Thomas M. Debevoise, Arthur Allen and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Tirades against war, Hitler. Pacifist campaigns, patriotic societies and Leagues. No Rockefeller support organizations in this file. Post-war fear of Russia, atomic bomb policies. World Government schemes. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John F. Dulles, Raymond B. Fosdick, Thomas M. Debevoise.
    110
  - Peace Plans - World Conditions - National Policy, 1946-1960 (Box 22, Folder 184)
  - Peace Plans - English Speaking Union
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gives $250 in 1922, repeated 1922-1924. Endorsed by Ivy Lee. Educational movement to better relations with England. Advisory committee gave $500 annually to journalistic fellowship, 1925-1929. Abby Aldrich Rockefeller made contribution in 1940-1941, also sent clothes. David Rockefeller became member, 1948. Mary French Rockefeller contributions. Laurance S. Rockefeller gift; became member in 1957; resigns in 1961. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller.
    110.1
    - 1922-1947 (Box 22, Folder 185)
    - 1922-1947 (Box 22, Folder 0185A)
    - 1948-1954 (Box 22, Folder 186)
    - 1948-1954 (Box 22, Folder 0186A)
    - 1955-1958 (Box 22, Folder 187)
    - 1955-1958 (Box 22, Folder 0187A)
      David Rockefeller became member, 1948. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
    - 1959-1961 (Box 22, Folder 188)
  - Peace Plans - English Speaking Union - International Relations - British/American, 1962-1965 (Box 22, Folder 189)
  - Peace Plans - English Speaking Union - International Relations - British/American, 1964-1966 (Box 22, Folder 190)
    Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    David Rockefeller material removed to Folder 190A.
  - Peace Plans - English Speaking Union - International Relations - British/American, 1964-1966 (Box 22, Folder 0190A)
  - Peace Plans - English Speaking Union - King George VI Memorial Fund, 1952-1958 (Box 23, Folder 191)
    Fund to bring young people from Commonwealth to United States for further study. Support of John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Dana S. Creel.
    David Rockefeller material removed to Folder 191A.
  - Peace Plans - English Speaking Union - King George VI Memorial Fund, 1952-1958 (Box 23, Folder 0191A)
    Fund to bring young people from Commonwealth to United States for further study. Support of David Rockefeller. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Peace Plans - English Speaking Union - David Rockefeller, 1950-1957 (Box 23, Folder 192)
    David Rockefeller's contributions to organization, Churchill Educational fund. Correspondents include David Rockefeller, William V. Griffin, Robert C. Bates.
  - Peace Plans - English Speaking Union - David Rockefeller, 1958-1961 (Box 23, Folder 193)
  - Peace Plans - World Alliance for International Friendship Through the Churches, 1925-1950 (Box 23, Folder 194)
    Request that John D. Rockefeller, Jr. sign and endorse statements on world peace. Refused. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. acted as absent sponsoring host at one dinner. A Subsidiary of the Church Peach Union. Correspondents include Fred B. Smith, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Raymond B. Fosdick, Harry Lunn.
    110.2
  - Peace Plans - World Alliance for International Friendship Through the Churches - Contributions, 1925-1930 (Box 23, Folder 195)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Advisory committee gave $10,000 in 1926, $200 toward 1926 dinner; $10,000 in 1927; $10,000 in 1927; $10,000 in 1928; $750 in 1928 toward a Goodwill Congress; $10,000 in 1929; $6,000 in 1930; $3,000 in 1931; $500 in 1933; $1,000 in 19232
  - Peace Plans - American Friends of Vietnam, 1955-1957 (Box 23, Folder 196)
    Organized to mobilize American support for the Diem regime in South Vietnam. John D. Rockefeller 3rd declined request to be one of sponsors. Gave small contributions 1957 to underwrite symposiums on vietnam. No continuing interest. Correspondents include A. B. Duke, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, D. McLeary, Dana S. Creel.
  - Peace Plans - American Friends of Vietnam, 1958-1961 (Box 23, Folder 197)
  - Peace Plans - League of Nations, 1925-1955 (Box 24, Folder 198)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributes to cost of handbook on International organizations. Small contributions to memorial fund for malarial martyrs. John D. Rockefeller 3rd's interest in League. E. V. Colby's analysis of League; League dissolved as United Nations takes over. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, E. V. Colby, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    110.3
  - Peace Plans - League of Nations - International Law Office, 1928-1929 (Box 24, Folder 199)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gives $12,000 for Industrial Relations sections.
  - Peace Plans - League of Nations - Pledge June 12, 1931, 1931-1936 (Box 24, Folder 200)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $50,000 toward study of disarmament.
  - Peace Plans - League of Nations - Pledge 1933, 1933-1934 (Box 24, Folder 201)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $5,000 to aid Jewish refugees fleeting Germany.
  - Peace Plans - League of Nations - Institut International de Cooperation Intellectuelle, 1934 (Box 24, Folder 202)
    Request declined.
  - Peace Plans - League of Nations - Intercollegiate Council, 1934 (Box 24, Folder 203)
    Request for student study of war declined.
  - Peace Plans - League of Nations - American Committee on International Intellectual Cooperation, 1927-1934 (Box 24, Folder 204)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributes.
  - Peace Plans - Union Now - Clarence Streit, 1939-1944 (Box 24, Folder 205)
    Requests for contributions declined. No real sympathy for Streit's program expressed by office. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    110.4
  - Peace Plans - Union Now - Clarence Streit, 1945-1958 (Box 24, Folder 206)
  - Peace Plans - Union Now - Clarence Streit - Publications, 1940-1956 (Box 24, Folder 207)
    Pamphlets prepared by Streit.
  - Peace Plans - Church Peace Union, 1928 (Box 24, Folder 208)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.. contributes $10,000 to Union for fostering of international cooperation. Followed by other small gifts. No contributions after 1931. The Union was founded in 1914 by Andrew Carnegie. Held international conference of religious leaders to discuss peace. Working for United States participation in World Court. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, Thomas B. Appleget, Willard S. Richardson.
  - Peace Plans - Church Peace Union, 1929-1956 (Box 24, Folder 209)
  - Peace Plans - Conference on Cause and Cure of War, 1924-1943 (Box 25, Folder 210)
    Began as Washington conference of National League of Women Voters. Between 1925 and 1933, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed $9,000 in annual installments. Reorganized in 1941. Nelson A. Rockefeller contributed $1000 in 1949. No other Rockefeller interest. Correspondents include, Thomas B. Appleget, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Raymond F. Fosdick, Arthur W. Packard.
    110.5
  - Peace Plans - Women's Action Committee - Bureau of Education for Lasting Peace, 1943-1946 (Box 25, Folder 211)
    Committee to unite American women to work for world peace. No action. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Mrs. Norman deR. Whitehouse.
    110.51
  - Peace Plans - National Council for Prevention of War, 1924-1950 (Box 25, Folder 212)
    Leader pacifist. Strong Quaker support. Program (Progressive World Organization, Armament Reduction, Education for Peace), progress of organization. Struggle against United States participation in World War II. Picked up in 1946--to prevent War with Russia. Correspondents include Kenneth Chorley, Raymond B. Fosdick, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    110.6
  - Peace Plans - National Council for Prevention of War - Contributions, 1928-1938 (Box 25, Folder 213)
    By Abby Aldrich Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.; only John D. Rockefeller, Jr. after 1928. Contributions made on Raymond B. Fosdick's advice to 1937, totaling $29,000. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Thomas B. Appleget, Raymond B. Fosdick.
  - Peace Plans - Fight for Freedom Committee, 1941-1942 (Box 25, Folder 214)
    Committee urged America's entrance into the war. Lambasted America First and Charles A. Lindbergh. Shifted to war work after December 7. Laurance S. Rockefeller contributed $500 in 1941. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed $4,000 in 1941. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller.
    110.7
  - Peace Plans - Advisory Committee on Research in International Law, 1925-1932 (Box 25, Folder 215)
    Committee engaged in codifying international law. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed toward research work through George W. Wickersham in 1926. Contributes to further work through Harvard in 1928. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard.
  - Peace Plans - World Peace Foundation, 1928-1959 (Box 25, Folder 216)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed $75,000, 1929-1931, to underwrite distribution of literature on world peace. David Rockefeller contribution. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, Arthur W. Packard, H. B. Faunce.
    110.8
  - Peace Plans - World Peace Foundation, 1928-1959 (Box 25, Folder 0216A)
  - Peace Plans - National World Court Committee, 1929-1935 (Box 25, Folder 217)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributes $5,000 toward education for world court in 1930, $2,500 in 1931, $1,500 in 1932, $500 in 1933, $250 in 1934, $500 in 1935. Correspondents include E. Colby, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    110.9
  - Peace Plans - International Peace Campaign, 1936-1939 (Box 25, Folder 218)
    Principal spirit of campaign to work for peace among the people was Lord Robert Cecil. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $15,000 in 1931 and 1932; $15,000 in 1936. Raymond B. Fosdick was initiating factor. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard.
    110.10
  - Peace Plans - International Free World Association, 1941-1945 (Box 26, Folder 219)
    Strongly patriotic organization. Information on policies and programs sent to Rockefeller office. No Rockefeller interest until 1945 when Nelson A. Rockefeller was on committee for banquet for President of Chile. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Nelson A. Rockefeller.
    110.11
  - Peace Plans - War Aims, 1942-1949 (Box 26, Folder 220)
    A fragmentary, scattered selection of programs for post-war world submitted to Rockefellers; no action by office. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
    110.12
  - Peace Plans - Pacifist Research Bureau, 1942-1943 (Box 26, Folder 221)
    Appeal for aid in educational work for pacifism. Declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
    110.13
  - Peace Plans - Commission to Study the Bases of Peace - John Foster Dulles, April 1942-April 1943 (Box 26, Folder 222)
    Committee set up in 1940 by Federal Council; Dulles in charge. Publications by Committee; John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s comments on them. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. makes small financial contribution. Significance here is John Foster Dulles. Correspondents include John Foster Dulles, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Thomas M. Debevoise.
    110.14